<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jurors judges of law and fact or, certain observations of certain differences in points of law between a certain reverend judg, called Andr. Horn, and an uncertain author of a certain paper, printed by one Francis Neale this year 1650. styled, A letter of due censure and redargution to Lievt. Col. John Lilburn, touching his tryall at Guild-Hall, London in Octob. 1649. subscribed H.P. Written by John Jones, gent. Not for any vindication of Mr. Lilburn against any injury which the said author doth him, who can best vindicate himself by due cours of law; if not rather leav it to God whose right is to revenge the wrongs of his servants. Nor of my self, but of what I have written much contrary to the tenents of this letter; and for the confirmation of the free people of England, that regard their libertie, propertie, and birthright, to beleev and stand to the truth that I have written, so far as they shall finde it ratified by the lawes of God and this land; and to beware of flatterers that endevor to seduce them under colour of good counsel, to betray their freedoms to perpetual slavery.</title>
            <author>Jones, John, of Neyath, Brecon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1414_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209436</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868319</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1414[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jurors judges of law and fact or, certain observations of certain differences in points of law between a certain reverend judg, called Andr. Horn, and an uncertain author of a certain paper, printed by one Francis Neale this year 1650. styled, A letter of due censure and redargution to Lievt. Col. John Lilburn, touching his tryall at Guild-Hall, London in Octob. 1649. subscribed H.P. Written by John Jones, gent. Not for any vindication of Mr. Lilburn against any injury which the said author doth him, who can best vindicate himself by due cours of law; if not rather leav it to God whose right is to revenge the wrongs of his servants. Nor of my self, but of what I have written much contrary to the tenents of this letter; and for the confirmation of the free people of England, that regard their libertie, propertie, and birthright, to beleev and stand to the truth that I have written, so far as they shall finde it ratified by the lawes of God and this land; and to beware of flatterers that endevor to seduce them under colour of good counsel, to betray their freedoms to perpetual slavery.</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, of Neyath, Brecon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.D. for T.B. &amp; G.M. at the three Bibles in Pauls church-yard, near the west end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "2d August".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judges --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169931:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JURORS JUDGES OF <hi>LAW</hi> and <hi>FACT:</hi> Or, certain Obſervations of certain differences in points of Law between a certain reverend Judg, called <hi>Andr. Horn,</hi> and an uncertain Author of a certain Paper, printed by one <hi>Francis Neale</hi> this year 1650. ſtyled, A Letter of due Cenſure and Redargution to Lievt. Col. JOHN LILBURN, touching his Tryall at Guild-Hall, London, in Octob. 1649. ſubſcribed H. P.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> JOHN JONES, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not for any vindication of Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> againſt any injury which the ſaid Author doth him, who can beſt vindicate himſelf by due court of Law; if not rather leav it to God whoſe right it is to revenge the wrongs of his ſervants.</p>
            <p>Nor of my ſelf, but of what I have written much contrary to the Tenents of this Letter; and for the Confirmation of the free People of England, that regard their libertie, propertie, and birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, to beleev and ſtand to the truth that I have written, ſo far as they ſhall finde it ratified by the laws of God and this Land; And to beware of Flatterers that endevor to ſeduce them under colour of good counſel, to betray their Freedoms to perpetual ſlavery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſtis vera dicens amico ad gratiam ſimulanti omnino perponendus eſt:</hi> An Enemy ſpeaking truth, is to be always prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before a flattering Freind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. D.</hi> for <hi>T. B.</hi> &amp; <hi>G. M.</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> church-yard, near the weſt end</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169931:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169931:2"/>
            <head>To the POLITIQUE BODIE, And Unanimous Fraternitie of the ARMY of ENGLAND; Officers and Souldiers, Ioyntly and ſeverally.</head>
            <p>HOnored and Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Commanders and Commanded: Wiſe and Prudent: Grave and Valiant: Seniors and
<pb facs="tcp:169931:3"/>Juniors: Souldiers all: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to moſt, Cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſom, ingaged to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; I preſume to write to you all, concerning what moſt concerneth us all: To Honor God: To love his Children: and hate, and quell his enemies, are his own Commandements: And although the two firſt be the greateſt, yet is the third none of the leaſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties required of us all, as appeareth by that account
<pb facs="tcp:169931:3"/>given by <hi>David</hi> ſaying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21. &amp; 22. Verſ. ſpeaking to God, <hi>Do not I hate them that hate thee? And am not I grieved with thoſe that riſe up againſt thee? I hate them with a perfect hatred, and count them my enemies.</hi> And the affliction of <hi>Saul</hi> for ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Agag,</hi> was a full exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to us in that caſe. Nay, an Heathen could tell <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> he did not his office when he
<pb facs="tcp:169931:4"/>forbore to puniſh diſhoneſt men. I confeſs, you have fought a good Fight, and declared your ſelvs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant workers in the waie of our Reformation, in our Land of Promiſe: promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many, performed by none, endeavored by too few. And I alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that you are now upon ſervice conducing in order to ſecure &amp; maintain the model to be perfected in time, from which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition
<pb facs="tcp:169931:4"/>I deſire not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert you, (as I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten formerly to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie the Lord General) but to give you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand you have left behind you more peſtiferous, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, obnoxious, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, ſedulous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant enemies to God, your Countrey, your ſelvs, and us all, then you have or can have, before you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that for ſparing thoſe at home unpuniſhed, as you
<pb facs="tcp:169931:5"/>might before you went, God will raiſe afflictions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you abroad, to make you minde your error be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you return; And let you know <hi>Achan</hi> and his Wedg muſt be diſcovered, and he and his Familie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at home, before you can expect proſperitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, for it is uſuall with God to ſend forraign Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recters to puniſh the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of his People that neglect the puniſhment of
<pb facs="tcp:169931:5"/>their domeſtique wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Many were our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans,</hi> even moſt of our Lawyers and Judges, that in the late Kings time Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly, and daily by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret briberies, and open extortions, exhauſted the treaſure of the people, even the whole eſtates, real and perſonal, of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the free-men of <hi>England,</hi> conſecrated to the ſaid free-men, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed upon them even
<pb facs="tcp:169931:6"/>by God himſelf, and his then Viceroy's, and the great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> atteſting their agreement thereupon. And this to be done (ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſomtimes Chief-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) under the Colour of Juſtice, is the greateſt kind of Injuſtice, and the cunningeſt Robberie that can be in the World. And do none of you know that we have ſtill ſuch as do the ſame? in compariſon of
<pb facs="tcp:169931:6"/>which and whom, <hi>Achan</hi> was but a ſole, ſillie, filch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thief; and his ſingle Wedg, but a poor trifling theft, nothing valuable to the leaſt ſhare of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt undertaker for draining <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> Fenns, and that is nothing in reſpect of the conſtant draining of the purſes of the reſt of that Countie, which alſo is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in reſpect of the reſt of all <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> more perfectly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb facs="tcp:169931:7"/>drained by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> then any Fen is or can be by Mr. <hi>Henley,</hi> and his partners. Nay, the extorted Fees for <hi>Habeas Corpus's</hi> from the Kings Bench and Fleet, yearly amount to a richer Wedg then <hi>Achans,</hi> which was no more then he could carri to his Tent of the ſpoyle of <hi>Jericho.</hi> Leſs loſs to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that were at libertie to fight for more, then what is daily
<pb facs="tcp:169931:7"/>and hourly carried by many of the price of ſtarv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings bread, to the ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chambers of ſeverall <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Judges; ſo loſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to hungrie Priſoners, that many thouſands of them loſe their lives by that means, before they can procure their libertie to ſpeak with their Creditors. Have we not had more men loſt ſo in dungeons in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impriſoned and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:169931:8"/>by Judges and Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, then you have loſt in the field, hurt by the hands of your enemies? And were not too many of thoſe (ſo loſt under the hands of Goalers and dooms of Judges) ſouldiers that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned ſafe from the mouths of Cannons, and the Swords of enemies, whoſe widows and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs children crie to men in vain for Juſtice and relief in this caſe? And ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:169931:8"/>God hear the crie of the poor, and of the blood of ſo many <hi>Abels?</hi> when men will not? I beſeech you lay theſe things to your hearts, and conſider in time; And let it not be ſaid that any of you accept bribes of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, to diſpence with their bribing, extorting and murthering of whom and as many as they pleaſe of your Friends, kindred and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen, whoſe caſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day may be your own,
<pb facs="tcp:169931:9"/>if you timely prevent it not. Som do inform you that they are beneficial men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; thoſe are falſ coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelors, for what can they give unto you, but what is none of their own? Nay more, but what is your own? forfeited and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged unto you amongſt the reſt of the Common-wealth, and ſo confeſſed even by their own mouths, (as I have written and proved formerly) be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:169931:9"/>pleaſed to make your ſelvs Maſters of your own whiles it is in your power, or expect it ſhall be told you the Virgins Lamp is out. If your preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement will not permit any of you to ſee this done, ceaſe not to ſollicit his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie to write to the Houſ, to deſire them to put out of their aſſembly al mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarie profeſſors of Law that poiſon their Counſell, no leſs then their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb facs="tcp:169931:10"/>did the King, making them to do the ſame things w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they condemned in him; to the more grief of the People, that were promiſed Reformation, and are paid in more and worſ deforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties then they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: witneſs amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie more abuſes, the Fen Project of <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> &amp;c. condemned in the late King, yet ſupported by more Malignant Royaliſts
<pb facs="tcp:169931:10"/>then in reſpect of Juſtice, he himſelf could be any, who are Judges, Parties and partners of the prey made by themſelvs of other mens Rights, of whoſe ſervice and affections, both Parliament and Army have had no leſs experience, then of their defects and delinquencies: And move his Excellencie to deſire the Houſe further to command the keepers of the great Seal to iſſue forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169931:11"/>and <hi>Terminer</hi> (as by Law they ought to all parties grieved, that ſhall demand them, directed to ſuch Commiſſioners as the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved parties ſhall nominat, to enquire hear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the extortions, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Sheriffs, under She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Gaolers, and other Officers ſubject to popular offence. And laſtly, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ſaid Houſe to paſs an Act for the ſetling of the
<pb facs="tcp:169931:11"/>Law hereafter (in that plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhortneſs and cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) as hath been often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired in divers Petitions of <hi>Londoners</hi> and others and by my laſt Letter to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, bearing date a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of this Month, according to the propoſitions of 12 heads of Law there incloſed which I underſtand in <hi>Scotland</hi> were delivered to his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies hands: So God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall bleſs you and
<pb facs="tcp:169931:12"/>your Actions, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple preſent and future, and even your ſelvs and your Children have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in your work, and be thankfull to God and your induſtrie for ſo great a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor. So ſhall</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Faithfull ſervant <hi>John Jones.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my Lodging at Mr. <hi>Mundays</hi> houſ in Clarkenwel, <date>this 29. of July, 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169931:12"/>
            <head>JURORS JUDGES OF <hi>Law and Fact:</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving caſually met with and peruſed your printed paper, ſtyled, A Letter of due Cenſure and Redargution to Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Collone <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> touching his Triall at <hi>Guild-Hall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169931:13"/>London:</hi> in <hi>October</hi> laſt 1649. I could not chuſe but take hold of your firſt Lines, wherein you ſay God's ſtrict Injunction obliges us all to <hi>reprove ſin</hi> whereſoever we finde it. And thereupon I muſt tell you, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you finde in Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> I can finde in you no leſs then ſin againſt God, whoſe name you abominably abuſe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove truth, and call good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and evill good: againſt Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> whom you make but your Inſtrument to play upon, while you wound others through his ſides, yea, even thoſe moſt, whom you flatter moſt: Againſt the true and Ordinarie <hi>Judges</hi> of the Land, the <hi>Jurors,</hi> whoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict is the effectual Judgement
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169931:13"/>whereby all men are judged by their Peers, aſwell for their Lives as Lands, without which Judgements, the Law of <hi>England</hi> cannot be Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie executed: And generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Free People of this Common-wealth, whom you endeavour to blinde and enſlave by your ſophiſtrie unto uſurped Authorities, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading (as much as in you lyeth) all your Countrie-men to ſubmit, and give away their Lives, their birthrights, Liberties, and Freedoms (for the preſervation whereof all their juſt Laws, and Civill Wars, and eſpecially this laſt, were made) to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Tyrannie of their incroaching Impoſtors, as ſhall appear following, <hi>viz.</hi> Page
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169931:14"/>3d, of your <hi>Letter</hi> (or rather <hi>Libell</hi>) in the ſecond head of thoſe things for which you ſay Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> is liable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, you tell him he laid hold of <hi>divers ſhifting Cavills, and ſhufling exceptions in Law,</hi> which were onely fit to waſt time, and procure trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Court; Sir! if Law alloweth Exceptions, called delatories, and lawfull Traverſes as well in Pleas for Land as for Life; as you may finde it doth and ought in Mr. <hi>Hornes</hi> Book called the <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Juſtice,</hi> written by him in French in <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt his time, as you may obſerve in the Margent of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page thereof, and excellently tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Engliſh lately by <hi>William Heughes</hi> Eſquire,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169931:14"/>a diſcreet and learned Lawyer living in <hi>Grayes Inn,</hi> of which kinde of Exceptions, ſome be Pleas for Actions and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales, the Preſidents where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are briefly and diverſly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of their cauſes, natures, and uſes, demonſtrated unto you in the ſaid Book, from <hi>p.</hi> 129. to <hi>p.</hi> 143. and thence to 146. are Exceptions, or Pleas to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments; the ſummary rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all which is not as you call it, to waſte time, and to procure trouble to Courts, but to beſtow time as it can be no better beſtowed (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Caſes of life) then to ſearch out the truth of every Cauſe, that mens lives be not raſhly loſt, which cannot be recovered if condemned and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169931:15"/>executed, how be it, wrongfully, or careleſly: ſo, that to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, circumſpect, and well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed in a Court is not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it, for it is its duty to be exerciſed as it is ſignificantlie derived à <hi>Curando;</hi> that is, a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Care,</hi> or <hi>Cure,</hi> Indifferentlie either, or rather both, as it is Ordained Care to be troubled to hear and determine the Cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of all men within its verge, for Controverſies of Law, (that vex &amp; trouble an whole hundred of Friends and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to ſee but two of them undoe themſelves in ſuits at Law, or kill one another) with Care to examin them tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to Judge them juſtly; And likewiſe to cure the Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie of the Conſciences, or at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169931:15"/>leaſt the intemperance of the Litigious ſpirits of Plaintiffs and Defendants, by ending their differences (as may be moſt available for their Peace, and the Common-wealth. And as it is the duty of a Court to be troubled to end troubles, ſo ſaith Mr. <hi>Horne p.</hi> 58. not to accuſe any for matters of Crime and Life, though a known offender, learning of Chriſt in the Caſe of <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len:</hi> Nor to countenance Bloody Accuſers, but to mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie their Rigour, as Chriſt did in the ſame Caſe; for Judges that repreſent God, and ſhould imitate his mercy as well as his Juſtice, ought not to <hi>deſire the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but rather that he may return from his wickedneſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169931:16"/>and live;</hi> and <hi>Conveniens ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini eſt hominem ſervare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas: Et meliùs nullà quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur Arte favor.</hi> Nothing more Convenient for Man, or acceptable to God, then to ſave Penitents, whom he came not to deſtroy, but to call to Repentance: Nor is it the part of a Judge (as in <hi>p.</hi> 66. of my ſaid Author) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn one for the ſame, or the like offence, as the Judge knoweth himſelf guilty of. And therefore Exceptions are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to the Power of a Judge, as in <hi>p.</hi> 133. to his perſon; as in <hi>p.</hi> 135. and to his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in <hi>p.</hi> 59. And thoſe that are granted to be lawfull to be propounded againſt his Power <hi>p.</hi> 133. are the ſame in ſubſtance, which you ſay Mr.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169931:16"/>
               <hi>Lilburne</hi> made uſe of, &amp; yet call them <hi>ſhifting cavills,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſhufling exceptions,</hi> &amp; reprove him for uſing them in defence of his life. I pray compare them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; then conſider what and whom you reprove; &amp; you can not chuſe but finde that for the matter, it is not a <hi>ſhifting cavil,</hi> or <hi>ſhufling exception,</hi> but the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid fundamentall Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> affirmed by all men that truly underſtand it, to be moſt Conſentaneous of all Laws, to the Law of God; And for the Perſons, it is not onely Mr. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> that deſired thereby to preſerve or prolong his life, but all the ſage makers, &amp; religious obſervers thereof, whereby you perſwade all your Countrimen preſent &amp; future, to diſeſteem ſuch exceptions (even to ſave
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169931:17"/>their lives) and conſequently to caſt themſelves away upon the wils, and haſt of Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Judges, who may be the onely, or chief Accuſers, or Adverſaries the Party queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for his life can have; which for any ſuch Partie to do, were to be more then mad, and even the Author of his own death, and of Gods Wrath upon his ſoul, which if he ſo wilfullie loſe, what is it to him to gain a world in lieu thereof? And why do you (more falſly then <hi>Caiphas</hi> that told one truth in his life unknown to himſelf) offer to perſwade us to becom wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſacrifice our ſelves one after another, to the lying bloody conſtructions of that Generall, and true Poſition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169931:17"/>
               <hi>Salus Populi, &amp;c.</hi> The Health of the Nation; is the chiefeſt Law; which you vaunt to be the empreſs of all your Maxims, whilſt you conſtrue it to the deſtruction of the Nation (as they are very ſenſible thereof,) and make it onely healthie to rotten Commiſſarie Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and corrupt Lawyers, whom you make the ſole Judges thereof; for what Chriſtian can bee ſo ſenſleſs as to believ, or conceiv, that the ſacrificing of any one man in that manner onely, for the ſuſpition (perhaps of no more then the Judge that findes himſelf moſt guilty of the Cauſe) as of being more able then another to raiſe or cauſe War againſt us; can avail us: For Sir! God delighteth not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169931:18"/>in bloody and dead ſacrifices, but in our humble, penitent, and lively Prayers, who are, or ought to be his living ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; And he that is as well the Lord of Hoſts, as the God of Peace, is our loving Father, and he will heare us when we call upon him in his Sons Name, and open his gate of mercie unto us when we knock as we ought, and whatſoever good we ask him in that name, he will not onely give it us, but moreover ſtrengthen us as he did <hi>Jacob,</hi> to wraſtle with himſelf, and to overcom his Anger, which an Heathen could underſtand and ſay: <hi>Flectitur iratus voce rogante Deus:</hi> Gods Anger ſtoopeth to his Childrens Prayers: And none but he can raiſe any warr
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169931:18"/>againſt them; nor will he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their ſins deſerve his puniſhment; and ſo farr; <hi>Is there any evill in Iſrael, but it is he that doth it?</hi> What do you therefore but ſhew your ſelf diffident of his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full omnipotence, and rob him of his Glory, when you attribute his power to man, to make War or Peace, and make your ſelf wiſer then he, when you think to prevent his will by your policie? and ſtronger then he, if you could deſtroy whom he would ſave? And therefore (ſaith <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton</hi>) Men are but fooles <hi>Vinculacùm tendunt impoſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe Jovi:</hi> when they ſuppoſe they can Chain the Dietie. And who can but ſee, that if it be granted you, that every
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169931:19"/>free man of <hi>England,</hi> whom you, or a Commiſſarie Judge, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, as bad, ſhall ſuſpect, or be pleaſed to accuſe for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition, of what you think good to invent, you may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe whom you will, and hang whom you liſt, and leave none to live, but at Lawyers diſcretion, whilſt the truch is, that ſo farr as any one man or more of any kind of men, whatſoever, can be called or accounted raiſers or cauſers of War in <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cook.</hi> Mr. <hi>Horne,</hi> and other ſound Lawyers tell you they ever were, and will be corrupt and mercenarie Lawyers, that ſell, delaie, and denie Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the beneſit of the great Charter of <hi>England</hi> to the People thereof; the due
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169931:19"/>puniſhment of whom, &amp; of all Sycophants that ſooth them up in their Errors, would be <hi>Salus Populi;</hi> for they are a conſiderable Army that have over-powred us theſe 500. years, Hyperprelaticall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; Domineering Nimrods; Undermining Pioners, (ſo that what was ſaid of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince the Popiſh Prelacy ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, may be ſaid of <hi>England</hi> ſince Lawyers overſwayed it, <hi>viz. Servierant tibi Anglia priùs domini dominorum, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ſervorum nunc miſeranda ſubes.</hi> O thou that wert the Lady of Lords, art the Slave of Slaves.) And a ſubtle and viperous generation that add Policie to their Power, to gnaw their Mothers bowels, and uſe to make diſſentions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169931:20"/>and Factions between even their own Brethren, to make work for themſelvs to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them, or moſt commonly by the ſtrength of the weakeſt, to deſtroy the ſtrongeſt, till they be able to Maſter both, and by right ſeldom, and wrong conſtantly, to make and keep themſelves rich, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever be poor, to accuſe and condemn all their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors for tyrannie, to make way for themſelves to be the onely ſuperviving ſupreme Tyrants, and compleat Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſians. The onely Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizers of Law, to ſell, delay, and denie Juſtice to the Free Men of <hi>England</hi> their Slaves, at their wills and pleaſures in their Congregational Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change <hi>Weſtminſter Hall.</hi> And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169931:20"/>whereas you ſay thoſe <hi>ſhifting eavils</hi> &amp; <hi>ſhufling exceptions</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> made uſe of, to waſte time, and procure trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Court, were far from making any defence for him: I pray you what defence could he deſire thereby but to ſave his life? And was not that done by the Verdict of a Jury, that heard what he ſaid for himſelf, received all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences that were given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and were Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ſworn to give their Verdict according to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: was not that Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict confirmed and ratified by the right Honorable the Councell of State, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the moſt Honorable and Supreme Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? without which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169931:21"/>by an implicit generall Warrant, or a ſpeciall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs: no man can be ſo mad as to think they would inlarge him? was not this as Full and fair a Triall as Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> could wiſh, or any man (Queſtioned for Treaſon) had theſe 100. years, or ſince Juries, (that underſtood Law no better then you) were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be bafled by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie Judges, and give what Verdict they pleaſed, as well for mens lives as their lands: did not his Exceptions and pleadings (whatever you call them) come near enough (how ever the Court liked them) to make him a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent defence in that mater? doth it not follow, that by your ſaid ſaying, you make
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169931:21"/>your ſelf a naked lyar? and can ſo apparent a lyar be a Creditalb reprover of ſin? the Devill he can as ſoon: doth it not further follow, that Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> hath his Action of the Caſe againſt you, for queſtioning him for the ſame offence that he is acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by ſo due a Courſe of Law? Doth it not moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver follow, that by traducing that Verdict and acquittall, you conſequentlie traduce, not onely the Jurie, but alſo the Councell of State, and the Parliament that Confirmed the ſame as aforeſaid? And are not you therefore lyable, not onely to the ſeverall Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of everie Juror, but alſo of <hi>Scandalum magnatum?</hi> But what need you care, you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169931:22"/>are too cunning for them all, in Concealing your name at large from them whom you ſlander at large, and ſend your Book to them with a <hi>ſine me Liber ibis in urbem;</hi> ſo that they know not when, where, or how to finde you out by that uncertain notion, or mark of <hi>H. P.</hi> Which for any thing I know, may fignify ſome Soap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff, as well as any mans name; but take heed leaſt <hi>John</hi> ſmell you out, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate you in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds for ſome ſimple corra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ingredient which he uſeth (not to any intent of malice, but to eat off ſom of your proud fleſh, and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy any ſound part in you, as you ſay in the title of your Book you uſe your reproof to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169931:22"/>him) to make a ſpeciall kind of ſoap to waſh the brains of ſuch Orators as perſwade men to becom ſuch fools, as to make no uſe of Lawfull exceptions againſt their Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (eſpecially Commiſſaries) to ſave their lives: and the tongues of ſuch Sycophants as under pretence of reproving the meaneſt, and weakeſt ſort of ſinners; approve, and improve the greateſt and ſtrongeſt kinde of Murtherers, Traytors, Perjurers, <hi>&amp;c. viz.</hi> Commiſſary Judges in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in their practiſe at large. But more to the matter, where you ſay in your 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> head, in the ſame 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> page of your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell: The 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> thing you ſay deſerveth a keen reproof of all honeſt men, was Mr. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnes</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169931:23"/>aſſayling the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Jury: and page 21. you ſay he promoted his 12. men, &amp;c. and cauſed them to imploy their new given Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, onely to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the giver. Truly Sir! I muſt confeſs, that if Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> aſſailed the ſinceritie of his Jury, he was to blame: but I cannot find by any thing you prove, that he did ſo, for the Clamor of the People (who were not his diſciples as you belie them and him too) were not in his power to ſtop, more then in yours, or mine, had we been there; for if they would not obey the Crier of the Court, they would not have obeyed us more then him, who deſired (as he need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) rather to be heard, then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169931:23"/>diſturbed, and diſtracted with Clamors. And for his blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments to his Jurie, good Language became him to give, and them to receiv, but not ſuch adulations as you give all Commiſſary Judges: And to uſe all the lawfull means he could to inform them, and all his Auditors that knew him not, nor his innocence in that Cauſe, and merit in others; and thereby to prolong his life in the Land which the Lord his God hath given him, and to keep himſelf a living ſacrifice to, and for his God, untill it pleaſe his Dietie to call him to his mercy by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie way of common death, or to inſpire him to fight again in his Maſters Battell and Countries ſervice: whereby
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169931:24"/>he may dye an extraordinary death, more to his Maſters glory, and his own honor, then by caſting away his life (to becom a dead ſacrifice to the malice of men, whether Commiſſary Judges, ſuch as you plead for; or other flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Sycophants, ſuch as you make your ſelf) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv to be no fault in Mr. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne.</hi> In the next place, where you ſay Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> promoted his 12 men to a new Juriſdiction; I am ſure, that is another Lie of yours, for you may read in the Lord <hi>Cooks Inſtitutions</hi> upon the 35 Chapter of <hi>Magna Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta:</hi> That County Courts, Court Barons, Sheriffs-Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and Leets, were in uſe before King <hi>Alphreds</hi> time;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169931:24"/>In all which Courts the Jurors were the Judges, &amp; their then untraverſable Verdicts were the Judgments in all Cauſes: And Sheriffs and Stewards, who were the Kings Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Judges in their Turnies, and Leets, as now they are the States, were, and ſtill are but the ſuitors Clerks in Counties, Hundreds and Court Barons, to enter their Judgments, and do executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereupon by themſelvs and their Bayliffs, as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſervants, or Miniſters of common Juſtice to their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth: See Mr. <hi>Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> Fo. 43. yet were they as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Commiſſary Judges by vertue of their Writs, when they have them for matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169931:25"/>4 <abbr>s.</abbr> as the Judges at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ever were, or can be by their Commiſſions: And all Common Pleas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Party and Party (and the King, Queen, and Prince were accounted but Parties as other Plaintiffs and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants in ſuch Pleas) were hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the County Court from Month to Month, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till for the eaſe of the People, eſpecially husband-men to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their buſineſs; The King with their aſſents divided the view of <hi>Frank pledg</hi> from the Sheriff who by all the Peoples affent in Parliament 9. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2d was to be thence forth aſſigned by the Chancellor, the Kings Commiſſiary Judge in his Turnies, (called before the Kings own Turnies) to ſee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169931:25"/>Juſtice done from County to County; And all the free pledges of every County toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, once every 7. years, which is ſince to be done by Sheriffs twice yearly) and gave them to Lords of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, ſo, that their Tenants and Reſiants ſhould have the ſame Juſtice in their Leets and Court Barons, as they had in the Sheriffs turnies and County Courts at their own doors without any charge, or loſs of time? And for the ſame reaſon (ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in the ſame place) Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds were divided from Sheriffs, <hi>viz.</hi> that none ſhould be troubled further, or out of their Lords Court at all; at which Courts (ſaith Mr. <hi>Horn</hi> p. 7.) Juſtice was ſo done,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169931:26"/>that every one ſo judged his neighbor by ſuch Judgment as none could elſwhere receiv in the like caſes, untill ſuch time as the Cuſtoms of the Realm were put in writing. And as the County Courts, Hundred Courts, and Court Barons were of one Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, ſo were Turnies, and Leets, and ſo all of them are, and ought to be ſtill; therefore you muſt conſider that there be three ſorts of Juriſdictions, <hi>viz. Soveraign; aſſigned,</hi> and <hi>ordinary:</hi> of theſe you may read in the <hi>Mirror? p.</hi> 7. in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> It was aſſented unto, that theſe things following ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Kings, and the right of the Crowne, <hi>viz.</hi> Soveraign Juriſdiction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169931:26"/>now fixed in the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> by vertue whereof among other things all Writs. Commiſſions, warrants, Commitments, &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berates or diſcharges run in their names as they did in the Kings, ſo that none are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonable, or diſchargable, but in their names; conſider therefore again that this aſſent was the Peoples, whereby Kings, (who before, and without this aſſent, were not Kings, but ordinary men, that could have but ordinary Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction as others) had So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Juriſdiction, as now the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of England</hi> have by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Parliament, which is the Repreſentative of the People, given them by the People
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169931:27"/>with a reſervation of their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary luriſdiction, <hi>viz.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in, by, and unto them in King <hi>Edward</hi> 1 his time, and ever before and ſince; by reaſon alſo of which ſoveraign and Royall Juriſdiction, as you may further read <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, p.</hi> 287. Kings were called and counted (as now the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> ought to be) foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Juſtice, and ordained becauſe they could not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies every where themſelvs, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did by <hi>Jethro's</hi> Councell, Inſtitute Captains over hundreds, Fifties, &amp;c. and now the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> do, and muſt ordain Commiſſary Judges, viz. Commiſſioners or Judges, by their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169931:27"/>miſſions or Writs to ſupply their preſence, and do their office in their ſtead, which in Courts, is but to give their aſſents to the verdicts, which are the judgments of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon their Peers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thoſe Judgments being ſo compleated, the executions thereof did do, and muſt run in the name of the Soveraign Juriſdiction of the State; And ſo Iuſtice may be adminiſtred in all places, in their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall abſence, who are to be accounted preſent in their Commiſſaries, who no more then their Maſters can be counted Iudges of the people, becauſe parties againſt them, and ſo made and named in, and by all Indictments, Writs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid. Obſerve
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169931:28"/>again, that Commiſſary Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, being ordained by their Maſters to do Iuſtice; if they fail of ſo doing by their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallitie, wilfullneſs, or any other conſideration, as <hi>Pilat</hi> (who was <hi>Caeſars</hi> Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) and others did (whom you aptly compare to ſom of them) then they have no juriſdiction, or ordination at all, ſo that they may be diſgracefully, and that lawfully pulled, and thrown out of their abuſed places: but in civilitie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Maſters may be better forborn, and referred to their Cenſures. And what is diſſenting, or not aſſenting to Iurors verdicts, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal, which is more then a failer of Iuſtice, for the ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof they muſt have
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169931:28"/>no negative voice: for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Iuriſdiction that was the ſupreme i that gave the Sove. raign (which is ſuperior to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſingular perſon) to Kings, (as now to the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi>) is ſtill the ſuperlative Iuriſdiction beyond all compariſon, that can be inferior to no authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but Gods, that gave it to his people, to his Children, not to be given by them, to any above them in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, but himſelf, from whom they have received, and to whom they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore themſevs and all that is theirs, but to be contrived, and ſubſtituted by them unto the worthieſt men amongſt them, to be imployed for and under them, as they might
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169931:29"/>finde moſt convenient for their worldly peace and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate government; to which end they deputed Kings, as now the Parliament hath don Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> reſerving ſo much of their ancient ordinary Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to free men, that none but ſuch may be Iurors, and none but ſuch may be their Iudges for their lives, lands, and eſtates: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Keepers of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties are ſubordinate to the Parliament, ſo are their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries to them, and both in their Iudgments, to the verdicts of the Iurors, which is their true ſaying of the whole matter, as well for Law, as Fact; and ſo is the full Iudgment of it, both in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169931:29"/>Law and effect, wanting onely the aſſent of the Soveraign Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, which is the onely party ſup poſed to be againſt the party guiltie, or ſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and hath that Majeſtie (or if well conſidered, that vaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage) given unto it, as to do, or command to be don Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; which, if the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man refuſe upon the Sheriffs command, the Sheriff him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf muſt doe; and if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, or neglect, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie Iudge muſt, for as there is a Writ <hi>de procedendo ad judicium,</hi> and an <hi>Alias, plures;</hi> and Attachment to compell him to give his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or, more properly, his aſſent (as aforeſaid) to the Iuries verdict: So that if he delay, denie, or faile to do,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169931:30"/>or cauſe Execution to be don, there is another Writ <hi>de exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutione Judicii,</hi> and an <hi>Alias, Plur',</hi> and Attachment upon that, to be had againſt him; whereupon, if a Commiſſary Iudg muſt be Attached for not giving his aſſent, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called his Iudgment) to a verdict for Fellonie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or having given his Iudgement to the verdict, ſhall denie or delay execution, except in ſpecial things hereafter touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let him not onely be an hangman for his Fellows, but be hanged himſelf; for ſuch was King <hi>Alfreds</hi> Iudgment in all Caſes of injuſtice in his Commiſſary Iuſtices, as you may read in the <hi>Mirror</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 239. to <hi>p.</hi> 245. when he hanged 44 of them in one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169931:30"/>year. But it is obſervable how Commiſſary Judges for Gaol deliveries do now a dayes uſe in the concluſion of their judgments upon Fellons; convicted by luries verdicts, and their aſſents, to command Sheriffs to ſee execution, and ſo to end their Seſſions; and get themſelvs gon out of that County with all expedition, and let the Sheriff and his hangman agree as they can bargain, for doing the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, while the Commiſſary impoſter proceedeth in his Circuit, attributing all that he findeth the people conceiv to be injuſtice, to the Sheriff, or Iury, or both, but calling all judgments and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (that are pleaſing to the people throughout his peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169931:31"/>and the Ambit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, even the Cirquit it ſelf,) his own; becauſe the people aſſented to ſuch Commiſſions, as the devill doth the world his own, becauſe God gave him leave to compaſs it; And as proud are ſuch Lords juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Lordſhips in a kinde, as he can be of his; yet in right ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted but ſervants to their Maſters, as he to his. And therefore whereas you ſay <hi>p.</hi> 24. though the verdict be given in upon the whole matter, and ſo incloſe Law as well as Fact, yet the binding force of the verdict as to matter of Law, may be derived from the ſanction of the Judges, not from the Iuriſdiction of the Inqueſt: And it may well be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169931:31"/>ſuppoſed that the Iurors may err in a matter of Law, in which caſe the Iudges muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the erroneous verdict by a contrary Iudgment, and that Iudgment queſtionleſs ſhall nullifie the erroneous verdict, not the erroneous verdict the Iudgement; whereby it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, That in a verdict upon the whole matter, there is no new Iuriſdiction acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Iurors in matter of Law, nor left to the Iudges; ſoraſmuch as the Iudgment ſtands good, and obligeth not as it is rendred by the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but as it is confirmed by the Iudges. Cana Man that would ſeem ſo Cornucopiouſly learned and wiſe as you do, be ſuch a fool, as to make ſuch a medley of nonſenſe; ſurely
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169931:32"/>ſhould you but tell ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſtorie in one of the Inns of Chancerie, the punieſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney there would hils you out of his mooting School. What error can be in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a true ſaying, but in the form there may, and that the Iudges and the Clerks aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be their office to make in Latin, and ſuch is the form, and Latin they uſually make thereof, that every word, or ſecond are commonly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, and that of purpoſe for themſelvs, to make work for themſelvs, by ſpinning the Cauſe in ſuites and vain plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſomtimes to ſeven years time, that might have been begun and ended in a day, and by beggering both parties to inrich themſelvs by dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169931:32"/>Fees and extortions, all that while? Can the verdict which is the true ſaying of 12. Men upon the whole matter of Law and Fact, be alter'd by a contrarie Iudgment, (as you expreſsly ſay you can) but that muſt be fals and an untrue ſaying, for what can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to a true ſaying, but a fals? And which of them ought to be altered? you ſay the verdict. Whereupon let all men judg whether you are not a plain liar therein, but ſuppoſe (ſince you goe by ſuppoſitions) that the ſaying of the Iurors is not true, and therefore no verdict, ſuch as Iudges receive, or rather ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and cauſe to be given them for verdicts by Iurors impanniled by Sheriffs, by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169931:33"/>Iudges directions for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Can the Confirmation of a Commiſſary Iudg, by his Iudgment make that good? Its a Maxim in Law, that what is naught in the <hi>foundation,</hi> can never be made good by <hi>Confirmation:</hi> but I confeſs many an honeſt man is hanged by ſuch ſuppoſed verdicts, and deviliſh Iudgments. Can ſuch Lies be called verdicts, or ſuch Iudgments be called true, more then you can be called a juſt reprover, or a due Cenſurer, that reprove truth, and juſtifie lying? Can the Devill be a worſe Cenſurer or Reprover? What Iudgment (mean you) ſtands good in Mr. <hi>Lilburnes</hi> Caſe, who had no Iudgment at all paſſed upon him, but that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169931:33"/>verdict that ſaved him, and the aſſent of the Councell of State, and Parliament that confirmed it? And what ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict or Iudgment do you finde fault with in all your Book over but that? Surely you were in a frenzie when you wove this ſtuff not ſo good as <hi>Linſey Woolſey;</hi> but if you would know what ſhould be done, in caſe a Jury ſhould give in an untrue ſaying, in ſtead of a verdict? (that being made to appear to a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Judg by the Partie grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or his Councell learned to be undeniably true; ſuch a ſeeming verdict, in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of life, or land of Free-hold, is traverſable; as alſo any ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict made defective, inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Lawyers as aforeſaid,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169931:34"/>and thereby ſounding defect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive in matter, and ſo counted erroneous by them that made it for that purpoſe, to linger the matter for their own gain, as you may read in Mr. <hi>Horns Mirror,</hi> as aforeſaid, and in the Statutes of 41. <hi>Edward</hi> 3. fol. 5. and 6. of <hi>Henry</hi> 7. and 19. <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit for bloodſhed in Leets there is no traverſe; becauſe the fact is a manifeſt wrong, and if laid upon a wrong per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he may have his Attaint againſt the Jury, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver treble damages, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of 24 better Jurors; which remedie every party wronged by any Jury hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Traverſe. And in caſe of life, which may be loſt (by the malice or ignorance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169931:34"/>of ſom Juries purpoſly return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſom Sheriffs for their own ends) if executed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſaying, and is never recoverable by Law: The Commiſſary Iudg upon true information and proof thereof, and not otherwiſe, ought to ſtay Iudgment, or execution, or both, untill he can likewiſe inform the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Englands</hi> Liberties of the truth of the Cauſe, and repriev the Priſoner untill their pardon or Tollerance be obtained for him, as was wont in the Kings time in like caſes, ſo, that afterwards the Priſoner may have his Attaint as he ought againſt ſuch a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whoſe Iudgment is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough for example to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſufficiently ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169931:35"/>to the Party, <hi>viz.</hi> to repair his wrong, and pay him treble damages: To for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit their lands and goods to the Lord of the Fee; to have their houſes demoliſhed; their woods rooted; their bodies impriſoned during their lives: And Iurors ought to try At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taints without Fee <hi>Ex officio,</hi> as you may read in the <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, p.</hi> 64. And ſo let ſo much ſerve in this place to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you that the Iuriſdiction of Iurors is to be Iudges and Verdictors of all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies given them in charge upon their Oaths, as well for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law as Fact; and as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient as, and more permanent then Commiſſary Iudges; for when Commiſſary Iudges had abuſed their places, ſo that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169931:35"/>they were beaten out of them, and Civill Wars therefore grew between Kings and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before <hi>Magna Charta:</hi> and ſince, untill the ſaid ſecond agreement made between <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and them, whereby Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Sheriffs were reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained (for they had been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before, as appeareth by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and long before that) to defend the Country when they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed of their guards, &amp;c. for till then guards continued for the breach of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> begun by <hi>Hugh de Burgo's</hi> means, and then Captains and Leiutenants became She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Coroners, &amp;c. and Centinels, Bailiffs, &amp;c. But alwayes the Free men judged their neighbours conſtantly;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169931:36"/>And therefore Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> neither did, nor could give his Iurors any new Iuriſdiction, nor promote them to any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment more then of right they had, (as you moſt falſly and maliciouſly, however ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly accuſe him, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe both him and them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the reſt of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths which follow, for next you ſay, that thereby you perceiv his Levelling Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy is, that Iudges becauſe they underſtand Law, are to be degraded, and made ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the Iurors; but the jurors becauſe they underſtand no Law, are to be mounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, where they are to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Law, to the whole Kingdom: the Iudges becauſe they are commonly gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169931:36"/>by birth, and have had honorable education, are to be expoſed to ſcorn; but the Jurors, becauſe they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly mechanick, bred up illiteratly to handy Crafts, are to be placed at the Helm, and conſequently Learning, and gentle extractions, becauſe they have been in eſteem in all Nations from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world til now, muſt be debaſed, but ignorance, and ſordid births muſt aſcend the Chair, and be lifted up to the eminenteſt Offices, and places of power, Coblers muſt now practiſe Phyſick in ſtead of Doctors, Tradeſmen muſt get into Pulpits, inſtead of Divines, and Plow-men muſt ride to Seſſions inſtead of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace. Sir, I ſhall not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169931:37"/>meddle with Mr. <hi>Lilburns</hi> Philoſophy, but ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv it more reaſonable, and therefore more tollerable then your ſophiſtrie, ſeeing it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by your own ſetting forth, his endeavour was not to degrade Judges becauſe they underſtood Law, but to inform them better, becauſe he conceived they underſtood not Law in his Caſe, till they would be pleaſed to be better inſtructed by his learned Councell, which (as he aledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed divers preſidents for) might have been as Lawfully allowed him, as thoſe that had them, for (as ſaith Mr. <hi>Horn</hi> 65 <hi>p.</hi> they are both neceſſarie and allowable to ſuch Clyents, as underſtand not Law them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs. And for none ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169931:37"/>as for their lives I think) neither doth it appear to be his purpoſe to make Judges ſervants to Jurors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they underſtood no Law, but to remember them to be ſervants to their own Maſters, to give their aſſent to the Iudgment of Jurors that he conceived did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Law: And what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der were it that theſe men, who by themſelvs and their predeceſſors did put the Laws of <hi>England</hi> (that had been in the Engliſh tongue intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all men whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) into uncoth Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of their own making, ſhould underſtand their own contrivance better then others who do underſtand Latin, French, Greek and Hebrew,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169931:38"/>better then moſt profeſſors of Law do, and Engliſh as well: What ſubverſion of the Law can be more then ſo to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it, that thoſe whom it moſt concerneth, can neither underſtand it, nor be excuſed by their ignorance in not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it, and ſo make it their net (whoſe libertie it ſhould be) and all to the end, that thoſe whom it concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth leaſt, or not at all, may elevate themſelvs by means of ſo unlawfull and preſtigiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and illiberal an Act, (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo harmleſs, nor ſo free and cheap as <hi>Canting</hi>) from little or nothing to great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, from <hi>Lourdeyneſs</hi> to <hi>Lords:</hi> And what can the ſubverſion of the Law (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch a ſubverſion) be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169931:38"/>leſs then treaſon againſt all the Engliſh Nation? But truly Sir! if Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Iudges ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſcorn, becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Gentlemen by birth, and honorably educated, I know none that will agree with him in that, nor can I believ it to be his deſire, that is known himſelf to be a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman born, honorably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, Civilly bred, marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſciplin'd, and very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally endowed beyond the capacities of ordinarie Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers. For learned, vertuous, and upright Judges howſoever born or bred, are to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored for their vertue, becauſe <hi>Honos eſt virtutis premium,</hi> Honor is the reward of vertue, and the better their births, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169931:39"/>educations be, the more fair and fortunate are their Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but <hi>Quamvis Caeſare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os enumeratis Avos:</hi> though deſcended of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated in his Court: They are not all of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that are of <hi>Iſaac:</hi> And golden Calvs are not to be adored. And if corrupt and vitious, you ſay Gods ſtrict injunction oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us all to reprov ſin where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we finde it: behold how you contradict your ſelf, when you would have all Iudges, becauſe wel-born, becauſe well bred (though as wicked as <hi>Pilat</hi> or <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> as you ſay elſwhere) to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by all men: And yet you would have ſin to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by all men whereſoever they finde it <hi>oportet mendacem
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169931:39"/>eſſe memorem:</hi> recover your ſelf by ſom diſtinction, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of policie, or elſ you are faln deep: <hi>Tende manus So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, &amp;c.</hi> I remember you ſay <hi>Jehojada</hi> did forbear <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> untill he gained more abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and better opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to accompliſh his deſires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her; I conceiv then you would have none to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov Judges but your ſelf; nor will you, till you have more advantage of them then you have yet; ſo the reſpit you give, is but till you have more advantage againſt them; not unlike that ſeſuiticall <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> which <hi>Ignatius</hi> never taught his Diſciples, but they learned it of his Maſter the devil: And therefore let the King of <hi>Spain</hi> take heed of it,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169931:40"/>for the Pope and they wait but opportunitie to ſwallow his Catholick Majeſtie into his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs bowels, when they preach one <hi>vicar</hi> in earth for one God in heaven: And let Judges take heed of your flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie which they may diſcern by your obligation, to reprove ſin whereſoever you finde it; and by your forbearance to reprove Judges (though never ſo ſinfull) untill you get op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie, and by your apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to fall down and worſhip them, all without diſtinction of good or bad; when ſom of them know themſelvs no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier to be worſhiped then he that our Saviour bad get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him. And what ſhall they be the better for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, if they dye before they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169931:40"/>have it? when you ought to ſpeak, <hi>de mortuis nil niſi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num;</hi> nothing but good of the dead; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> more graciouſly reproved <hi>Peter</hi> to his face, when and where he found him faulty. As for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors placing at the Helm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe mechanick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you touch not Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> for his Jurors (as all others in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ought to be) were impan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neled by the Sheriffs of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or their ſecondaries, who knew them to be honeſt lawfull men, ſuch as their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept required, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad the Judges any cauſe to ſuſpect, refuſe, or chang them, they had done by them all, or ten at leaſt as they did by one of them, take in others for them: And you ſay that Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169931:41"/>excepted againſt them all, and deſired to be tried by a Jurie of <hi>Surrey,</hi> where he lived when the Fact was ſuppoſed to be committed, (and if by him, liklieſt to have been there) where a Jurie might be had of no mechanicks, but God, who (as you ſay elſwhere, and that truly, as the devil, to be believed in more, uſeth to tell ſom truths) is preſent in all Courts, was really, though not viſibly preſent there, and had fore-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better for his ſervant, then he knew how to deſire; A Jurie of Mechanicks, whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Eſtates I know not, but their carriage and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that matter declare them knowing and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Men, Confirmed in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169931:41"/>their Verdict, firſt by God himſelf then doubtleſsly not onely preſent in the Court, but in their hearts and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: And afterwards by the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>State</hi> by aſſent of <hi>Parliament:</hi> A Preſident for Jurors, and a memorable example of undantable, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable, conſciencious Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of life and death, for the preſent, and all future ages to imitate: yet traduced by you, and in them God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Author of the work, and the State, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel Cooperaters therein. And no mervel for al that, ſince you cannot be content to calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate all that had a hand in the matter, but alſo the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all the conſtant Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of all Cities and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169931:42"/>in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> of whom not one in a Million, ever knew Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> or heard of his Cauſe, all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks. For what Trade, or myſterie of Merchandize can be, but hath its original from ſom handicraft? What Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſo eaſie or carleſs, but ſomtimes uſeth the help of his own hand, or ſervants to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or weigh his commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for which he ventureth his life, or others, and his Eſtate to boot, to fetch them from the Indies, and why ſhould he ſcorn to put his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to retail them to his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers by true weights and meaſures? And ſo I conceiv writing is but an handi-craft taught a Lawyer before mooting, and neceſſarie to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169931:42"/>be uſed by him when he is a Judg, whoſe (dutie as the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> upon the 29 <hi>chapt.</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> ſaith, is, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernere per Legem quid ſit juſtum:</hi> to deſcern what is juſt by the rule of Law; and ſo to make the Law his rule, his line, his meaſure, his weight, his yard and ballance, which (ſaith the ſame: Author in the ſame place) is called <hi>Right it ſelf,</hi> And <hi>Common Law;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it judgeth common Right, by a right line, which is the Judg of it ſelf and its oblique. And in another ſenſ (ſaith he) the <hi>Law</hi> is called <hi>Right,</hi> becauſe it is the beſt Birth-right the Subject hath, whereby his goods, lands, Wife, Children, bodie, honor and eſtimation are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169931:43"/>from injuries, and ſo a better Inheritance cometh to everie one of us by the Law, then by our Parents: but when appropriated by Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to their own conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and benefit, how is it to becalled common Law?) and when a Commiſſarie Judg like Pluto's Radamanth, maketh his will his Rule and line, and thereby ſquaretth and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth the Law as he pleaſeth, and as <hi>Virgil</hi> diſeribeth him: <hi>Groſius hic Radamanthus habet duriſima regna, &amp;c. Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gátque Auditque dolo, ſubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitque fateri leges fixit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio atque refixit, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt he puniſheth, then he heareth, and compelleth to confeſs, and ſo maketh and marreth Laws as he pleaſeth for his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169931:43"/>profit: ſuch are the Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries I deſire to reprov, and you to flatter: but I wiſh them to obſerv <hi>Cryſippus</hi> his Picture of Juſtice deſcribed in a Latin Diologue thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quae Dea? Juſtitia: at quid torva lumina ſlectis?</l>
                  <l>Neſ ia ſum flecti, nec moveor prctio.</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde genus? Coelo. Quite genuere Parentes?</l>
                  <l>Mî Modus eſt genitor, clara fides Genitrix</l>
                  <l>Auriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aperta tibi cur altera, &amp; altera clauſa eſt?</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na patet juſtis, altera ſurda malis.</l>
                  <l>Cur gladium tua dextra gerit? Cur laeva bilances?</l>
                  <l>Ponderat haec cauſas, percutit illae reos.</l>
                  <l>Cur ſola incedis? quia copia rara bonorum eſt;</l>
                  <l>Haec referunt paucos ſecula Fabritios.</l>
                  <l>Pauperc cur Cultu? Semper juſtiſſimus eſſe,</l>
                  <l>Qui cupit, immenſas nemo parabit opes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169931:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Engliſhed by me thus.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Goddeſs art thou? Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: why ſo ſtern?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No force ſhall make me bow; nor brible me yearn.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whence ſprung? from heaven. What parents gave thee breath?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Indifference was my Father; Mother, Faith.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why open'ſt one ear, ſhutt'ſt the other ſtill?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One hears the good, the other's deaf to ill.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why right hand ſworded? ſcald the left appears?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One weighs the Cauſe, the other cuts guilts ears.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why art alone? becauſe few good there be;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scant one <hi>Fabritius</hi> in this age we ſee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169931:44"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why poor in Robe? becauſe who would be juſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No vaſt eſtate or Wardrobe purchaſe muſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>But I obſerv that as the meaneſt handicrafts man, when he groweth rich, turns Merchant, that he may live Lazier, and gain more by buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling merchantable Commodities, then by his labor, yea, and the craftieſt Merchant of all; or as lately the pooreſt Schollars being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto Wealth, became Biſhops by the ſame means, and for the ſame reaſon; yea, and the preciſeſt formaliſt of all, ſo the ſimpleſt mooter in the Inns of Chancerie, being being paſt his Apprentiſhip, admitted to the bar, and but botching Jorneyman in the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169931:45"/>trade of Law, furniſhed with money friends and fortune, proceedeth Sergeant at Law, and aſcendeth ſom Chair, or Bench of Judicature in a day, and declareth himſelf preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the pragmaticaleſt Judg of all, yet but a Commiſſarie Judg, ſuch as you extol in the generall, and I except againſt in ſom particulars, as for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law a mercenarie trade, or a merchantable commoditie, which ought to be free and liberall to all men; and in aſſuming a Maſterſhip therein, whereas he is and ought to be but a ſervant to the Common-wealth; yea, even a Clerk (though you ſeem to repine at it) to ſay <hi>Amen, viz.</hi> to pronounce his Maſters aſſent to the verdicts
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169931:45"/>of <hi>Jurors</hi> who by their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Iuriſdiction are the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Judges of their Countrie, as before is proved. Yet ſhall I be content to follow your Follies a little further for your better ſatisfaction touching Mechanicks, who buy and ſell but what are vendible and merchantable wares, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them ſo to do, which if by unreaſonable penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths, their reaſonable Cuſtomers may take or leave as their occaſion requires, and reaſon guides them: whilſt Lawyers Clyents muſt buy ſuch Law as they can finde, at ſuch rates as they can get at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or periſh in their Cauſes: different from thoſe times, when Mr. <hi>Horn,</hi> and others tell you, they had
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169931:46"/>better brought to their own doors with little charge, and leſs pains: and when to ſee it ſo adminiſtred and executed by Sheriffs, Recorders, and other Countrie and Citie Judges, that were the Kings Commiſſaries in their reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive places, and derived their Commiſſions and authorities as well as any at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ever did, or can, from the ſame fountain, <hi>viz</hi> Kings and people, ſo that (as the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſaith) <hi>Omnis dorivata poteſtas habet eandem juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem cum primitivâ:</hi> their juriſdictions were the ſame within their precincts, as the Kings at larg; yet Kings went along with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, or rather Deputies, for their own Bench, from
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169931:46"/>Countie to Countie, once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſeven years, to overſee, and examin how Juſtice was diſtributed to their Subjects, and to give their Royal aſſents to the verdicts of Juries which were not aſſented unto by the ordinarie Countrey Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſince the laſt Size: which Commiſſioners therefore one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not the Countrey in generall, (as now to Aſſizes, <hi>niſi prius,</hi> and Gaol delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) or ſo much as the Jurors were called, or troubled to bring in any account of what they had done ſince the laſt Eire, but thoſe Commiſſarie Officers onely for that they had not done were charged to bring in their Records, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuch verdicts as were found unaſſented unto and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169931:47"/>compleated by them, might be aſſented unto and perfected by the King himſelf, or his Commiſſarie Judg, or depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, called his chief Juſtice of his own Bench; or by the Juſtices in Eire, who went ſomtimes without the King, or any of his Juſtices, who when and where they came, had the prerogative of all Courts during their ſtay, which was but for ſhort Seſſions) &amp; gave forth proceſs of execution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and medled not with any mors Cauſes, but onely within his verge, by the verdicts of Iurors inhabiting within the compaſs, as you may read in the <hi>Mirror, Lambert</hi> and others at larg. And why now all muſt come to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> four times
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169931:47"/>yearly; and no cauſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther over or under 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> can be ended in any part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom but there; for if under <hi>á Mutuatus</hi> ſhall lift it over, and all under colour of that Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which ſaith Common Pleas ſhall not follow the Kings Court (as his <hi>Bench, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie,</hi> and his <hi>Exchequer</hi> then did and ever might) but ſhall be kept in a certain place; which came to be <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Hall</hi> ſince it was the Kings pleaſure to have that Court (which was their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative ſuperindendent Court of Common Pleas, <hi>viz.</hi> for Appeals in ſuch Pleas, by ſuch as found themſelvs grieved by partialities or delaies of their Countrey Commiſſaries, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169931:48"/>that Court) kept in their own Hall, of their then dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Manſion, as it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed untill <hi>White-Hall</hi> came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. by Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencie, which (pleaſing him better) he madehis Court; and gave not onely <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Hall,</hi> but alſo all the Pallace of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (that his Anceſtors from <hi>Rufus</hi> to him, contented themſelvs to dwell in) to be the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all his Courts, when he found it chargable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them, though he and his ſucceſſors gained leaſt by them. But now no King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no Court that depended upon his Perſon, or his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Commiſſaries, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their prerogative Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169931:48"/>reputed tranſcendent remedies for ſom tranſcendent Injuries committed and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt the people, can be neceſſarie, becauſe triennial or more frequent Parliaments, and ſpeciall Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> to be granted them, when and as their Cauſes require, may better ſupply them and with more ſpeed and Juſtice, and leſs charge and expence finiſh their Cauſes at or near their homes, then all, or any the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ever did or could. But if the <hi>Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of <hi>Englands Libertie</hi> be pleaſed to have any one or more Courts, or Judges to be ſuperintendents above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beſides Parliaments, and ſpeciall <hi>Oyers</hi> and <hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169931:49"/>Then they are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, to be alſo pleaſed to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and pay them ſufficient Wages at their own coſt, and not the peoples, as Kings did when their Commiſſarie Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es were to have of never ſo many Parties in one Cauſe, but 12<hi rend="sup">d</hi> to be divided amongſt them, and that after the end of the ſuit, and not before: And a Pleader (though a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant at Law) was ſworn to plead as well as he could for his Maſter (now called his Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and counted his ſervant) and to abuſe the Court with no falſ, or more delatorie then neceſſarie Pleas, And was to have for every ſuch Plea pleading, but ſix pencel; and for his ſallarie or Wages, for his attendance in every Cauſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169931:49"/>firſt to laſt, beginning to end, as the Court ſhould think fit, conſidering the greatneſs of the Cauſe, and merit of the Pleader, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as you may read in the <hi>Mirror, p.</hi> 64. Now to return to your Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, commonly (as you ſay) brought up illiterat: ſurely it cannot be unknown to you, that there are moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as many (if not more) Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Art in <hi>London</hi> that uſe Trades and handicrafts as practiſe Law at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and compleater Retoritians, Logitians, Muſitians, Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metitians, Geometricians, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomers and Phiſitians, all which are the ſeverall liberall ſciences, and the very Ency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clopedie and ſummarie of all good and neceſſarie Arts and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169931:50"/>learning: How then do you make it your conſequence, that if all Commiſſarie Judges be not adored as you would have them; all learning and gentle extraction muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed, but ignorant and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did birth muſt aſcend to the Chair? as if there were no learning but in Pedlers French and Law-Latin, the very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of the Law, which hath no ſuch need of them, as a foul face of a Mask, or an hangman of a Vizard; but contrariwiſe, much neceſſarie to be rid of thoſe Curtains, which hide both the beautifull Shape, and material ſubſtance of it, from us, that it may appear (even to our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings) more gloriouſly, more learnedly in plain Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169931:50"/>then in that Canting more obnoxious then that of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, which would but cheat us of neceſſaries to ſuſtain their lives; whilſt <hi>Law-Cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> cheat both us, and them, of all our livelihoods and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, to ſurfet themſelvs with ſuperfluities; by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us all ſtarvlings, pined with that extream of wants, the want of <hi>Juſtice:</hi> for put the caſe that thoſe <hi>hotch-potch French,</hi> and Quelquechoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin were baniſhed, and the Law rendred in Engliſh (as Scriptures are which were hidden from us by Prelats, as our Law by Lawyers) would not all learning, and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations in Law be as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for the continual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of mens lives and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169931:51"/>and therefore continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Engliſh as Sermons in Pulptis, and diſputes in Schools and Univerſities, requiſit for the ſalvation of our ſouls are? Naywould not School-Maſters (to read and teach the Law in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Schools) beas ne ceſſarie in <hi>London,</hi> as Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the Inns of Court, or Chancerie, or as ſuch have been (as you may read in the Lord <hi>Cooks Preamble</hi> upon <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) and did read upon <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> when it was read twice yearly in Churches, and 4 times yearly untill full Counties, untill the ſame King that aſſented to the making, and was ſworne to the obſerving of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> in the 9 year of his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169931:51"/>Raign, by the advice of his Chief Juſtice <hi>Hugh d'Burgo</hi> (whoſe advice and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ever led Kings to ruine, and Subjects to hazards) by his ſpecial Writ in the 19 year of his Raign, prohibited the ſaid publick reading, and teaching, (as you may read in the ſame place.) Did not the <hi>Eunuch</hi> underſtand the Language he read, yet want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Philip</hi> to interpret the meaning? And did not God ſend <hi>Philip</hi> to that end? So no doubt (although the Law be Engliſhed) the moſt part of Engliſh people will be <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs</hi> in their underſtanding of it ſo fully as they ought, untill, and but whilſt there be <hi>Philips</hi> to expound it? for it is too great a Studie for men
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169931:52"/>otherwiſe imployed, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in; to reſolv Cauſes which you call Intricate, As you would make it for Coblers to dilucidate texts, which many call hard Scriptures: And who can doubt it to be Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall gift and vocation in Law to ſom, to be juſt and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lawyers, as to others to be ſincere and Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, while the world ſhall conſiſt of bodies neceſſarie to be regulated, as of ſouls to be diſciplined. And then for your gentle extractions, may not they be as they were ever wont (ſince Marriages were ordained in Heaven, may not a Judg beſtow his daughter upon a Citizen, and a Citizen his upon a Judg, or an Earl, (as we have ſeen uſuall): but
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169931:52"/>by your allegation that there is a general diſeſteem of gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie more now then from the beginning of the World, which Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> can be no cauſe of: It is manifeſt you charge the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as faultie for ſuffering ſuch a diſeſteem to be among the people, wherein you do but traduce and wrong the State, that neither deſire, nor countenance any ſuch thing, but when gentrie (for the moſt part) grows dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat, and nobilitie debaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelf, <hi>Corruptio unius eſt generatio alterius:</hi> when Lords turn Boors and ſimplicians, let Clowns turn Lords and Politicians; And let him that will carp at the Viciſſitude of things, which divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169931:53"/>hath ordained, blame neither State in generall, nor perſons in particular, but conceiv rather, that <hi>Ablatâ Cauſâ tollitur effectus;</hi> when vertue faileth, the honor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; when God took his holy Spirit from <hi>Saul,</hi> both Spirit and Majeſtie were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to <hi>David</hi> in a larger meaſure; and therupon be you further anſwered by an Hea then: <hi>Tempora mutantur, et nos mutamur in illis:</hi> Times are changed, and we therein: By whom, is manifeſt; but how, and when, are <hi>Arcana Dei:</hi> Forbidden ſecrets, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable by ſuch as ſuffer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to their ſins; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhew your ſelf in this point, not an <hi>Alter Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> but an <hi>Altercator:</hi> not a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169931:53"/>wiſe man but a wrangler: Whilſt you might obſerv further, that God never took his holy Spirit from whom he gave it, but for their abuſing, or not uſing that power which accompanied it, as they ought, whereby they provoked him, as when he ſaid: <hi>It repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me that I have ſet up Saul to be King:</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 15.11. When <hi>Saul</hi> ſpared <hi>Agag,</hi> and his fat Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which God commanded to be deſtroyed: So when <hi>Englands</hi> Kings and Lords made wrong uſe of their Judicature and power which he and his people had given them; was it not time for God himſelf, to juſtifie himſelf and his people? When they and their ſubordinate Judges connived together
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169931:54"/>with ſuch men as God deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to be his enemies, ſaying: <hi>Among my people are found wicked men, they lay wait, as he that ſetteth ſnares, they ſet a trap, they oath men, and as a Cage is full of birds, ſo are their houſes full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, therefore they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great and waxen rich; they are waxen fat, they ſhine; ye, they overpaſs the deeds of the wicked, they Judg not the Cauſe of the Fatherleſs, yet they proſper; and the right of the needie do they not Judg: ſhall I not viſit for theſe things (ſaith the Lord)? ſhall not my ſoul be avenged upon ſuch a generation as this? Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 26. were there ever in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuch waylayers, ſnare-ſetters, trap-ſetters,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169931:54"/>and men-catchers, as were the Scribes and Phariſes, who concealed the Law (which God made for his people) and aſſumed the expoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be proper to themſelvs only, and thereby ſnared, trapped, and caught the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as they pleaſed; made way for themſelvs to becom great, rich, fat and ſhine; which expoſition was but of their own naturall language, which their Countrey-men underſtood, or might as well as they, yet our Saviour cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them <hi>a generation of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, &amp;c. that laid heavie yoaks upon their brethren, &amp;c.</hi> Did not our Judges and Atturneyes in <hi>England</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them, that not onely concealed the Laws of God,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169931:55"/>and this Land, made for this people, from this people? though partly publiſhed in Engliſh (as our Statute Laws are) whereof nevertheleſs they aſſume the expoſition to themſelvs; howbeit rational Engliſh-men may underſtand them as well as they; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo barbarized that part of our Law which is called, and ought to be common, ſo that they have made it proper to themſelvs onely, becauſe no other linguiſt (howſoever learned) can underſtand it, but onely they that made it ſuch for that purpoſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſnare, and trap all men as they liſt, and their Legion Gaolers, Catch-poles, ſetters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (who glorie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in thoſe names, and are
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169931:55"/>rich by thoſe meanes) catch, and impriſon all Debtors, and moſt of them to death, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Law, but what they made and procured againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and maintain (though repealed) againſt the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and above 20. Statutes, all Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> Do the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> judg the Cauſe of the Fatherleſs? the Orphans of <hi>London</hi> can tell you no. Do they judg the right of the needie? the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, the Fatherleſs, and all that ſue <hi>in formâ pauperis,</hi> nay they that beg, rob, and ſteal to boot, with thoſe that ſtarv for need, can tell you no. And ſhall not God be as good as his word? <hi>Shall not his ſoul be avenged upon this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:169931:56"/>yea, no doubt, and therefore Judgment began at the Houſe of the Lord, which King, Lords and Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops, that parted the peoples ſpoyls, neglected <hi>Achan</hi> and his Wedg; made all covetous gripers more griping, <hi>Regis ad exemplum;</hi> and all men more offenders becauſe the greateſt moſt thrived, and were never puniſhed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Kings, Lords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whoſe extractions for Gentrie were ever eſteemed beſt; And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Biſhops well deſcended, laying aſide their vertues, who ſhall blame God for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their honor in the duſt? but let all that love the preſent State, and Government of <hi>England,</hi> wiſh the Keepers of the Libertie thereof, take heed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169931:56"/>in time they do not the ſame things themſelvs, they have condemned in others, of whoſe puniſhments God hath made them his Inſtruments; for we are ſure that the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God is according to truth, againſt them which commit ſuch things;</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Let them not overpaſs the ſeeds of the wicked, by not puniſhing them which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nde to be ſuch, yea, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially the wickedeſt of them, even ſuch as none can be ſo wicked; Judges that perſevere in injuſtice, who by ſuffering ſuch offenders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com not onely the committers of their offences, but ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive offenders, whom God nath none above them to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, but himſelf, which he
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169931:57"/>therefore uſually doth, by raiſing Wars againſt them, and enemies unto them, as well of their own Nation, nay their own Children, as others; and as well Inſideators of their wayes to, and at their dores, and aſſacinates in their houſes, as adverſaries in the Field. And as for your ſelf Sir, may not we ſay of you, as <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſaid of ſom in his time: <hi>A Wonderfull and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing is committed in the Land, that Prophets Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie falſly, &amp;c.</hi> For what do you elſ when you ſay, you are obliged, as all men are, to reprov ſin whereſoever you finde it, and yet you juſtifie and magnifie ſuch Judges as the true Prophet reproveth. Take heed therefore how you
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169931:57"/>uſe your <hi>tertiam Linguam</hi> (as <hi>Walterfenſis</hi> cals it) which by lying and ſlandering, either by way of <hi>adulation,</hi> as you do the Judges, or <hi>detraction,</hi> as you do Mr. <hi>Lilburn:</hi> the partie that ſo doth, abuſeth three perſons at once, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Speaker,</hi> the <hi>hearer,</hi> and he that is <hi>ſpoken of:</hi> And ſuch leagues (ſaith the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) had the Prophets that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ere ſlain; <hi>Doeg,</hi> that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſected, and <hi>Saul</hi> that ſlew himſelf: And ſuch tongues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t. <hi>Bernard</hi> cals triplicit, for the ſame reaſon; and ſaith, that ſuch Sycophants as uſe them, have the <hi>Devil</hi> in their tongues, and <hi>Auditors</hi> in their eares, and a <hi>conſenter</hi> in their hearts. And for ſordid births (except I knew yours) I know
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169931:58"/>not what to ſay to you; but ſuppoſe the tree may be known by the fruit, and well do I know, that as <hi>London,</hi> and other Cities, ever had Mechanicks of as great and noble extractions, as <hi>England</hi> yeilded, ſo the Barrs at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> ever hitherto had long-roabed men of as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous originals, as huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie afforded: And of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> births at this preſent, there be vertuous and honorable Chair-men at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as <hi>è converſo,</hi> there be of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſons, hopefull Apprentiſes in London. Where you finde <hi>Coblers</hi> in Pulpits, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Divines</hi> are out. And where you ſay Plow-men ride to Seſſions inſtead of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace; there can be
<pb facs="tcp:169931:58"/>no Seſſions without both, <hi>viz.</hi> Knights or Eſquires to be Juſtices, and Plow men, (which are the beſt kinde of free men in <hi>England</hi>) to be Jurors. And as Jurors are there, and elſwhere the more real Judges, ſo is their calling far antienter, for <hi>ſokmen</hi> were long before Juſtices of Peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England;</hi> And ſoccage was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a better tenure then <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>cage,</hi> or Knights ſervice. But a Juſtice of Peace, and a Plow-man do well together, not onely in Quarter-ſeſſions, but in conſtant houſ-holds; and the eminenteſt, beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racted Knights and Eſquires, as they have ever been the beſt houſ-keepers, ſo they have been the bountifuleſt cheriſhers and countenancers
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169931:59"/>of their Plow-men in their moſt neceſſarie calling for the Worlds ſuſtenance: and have not ſcorned to put their hands to their own plows, as Kings and Lords have vouchſafed their names, and aſſociacions to their Subjects, in their trades and handicrafts, to countenance, commerce and traffique.</p>
            <p>So not finding any more o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Pamphlet neceſſarie for me to anſwer, as this much was, for my reaſon given you in the title page thereof. I bid you heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my lodging in Mr. <hi>Mondays</hi> houſe upon <hi>Clerkenwell-Green,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169931:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
